<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of riches discovered in a sermon / preach'd at St. Pauls, Septemb. the 28th 1662 before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor by Thomas Cartwright ...</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15565476</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15565476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103829</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103829)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1588:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of riches discovered in a sermon / preach'd at St. Pauls, Septemb. the 28th 1662 before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor by Thomas Cartwright ...</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Davenport for John Baker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XIX, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Wealth --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103829:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER OF RICHES, DISCOVERED IN A SERMON PREACH'D At S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Paul's, <hi>Septemb.</hi> the 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1662. before the Right Honorable the Lord Mayor.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS CARTWRIGHT</hi> D. D. and Chaplain to His Majeſty.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Hierocl. in Carm. Pythag.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Davenport</hi> for <hi>John Baker</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Peacock</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church Yard. 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103829:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103829:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>JOHN ROBINSON,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lieutenant of His Majeſty's Tower, and Lord Mayor Elect of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext to his <hi>Innocence</hi> there ought nothing to be dearer to a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> than his <hi>Reputation,</hi> who as long as he lies under an <hi>ill character,</hi> will rather <hi>teach</hi> the People to <hi>find fault</hi> with <hi>him</hi> than <hi>mend any</hi> in themſelves; and therefore he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in duty to <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> to clear his <hi>words</hi> from all <hi>miſ-priſions,</hi> and his <hi>actions</hi> from all <hi>aſperſions</hi> which are at any time caſt upon them; in <hi>which reſpect it is,</hi> that I am now concern'd to ſubmit to the <hi>publick cenſure</hi> this <hi>following diſcourſe,</hi> which I lately deliver'd in a Sermon at St.
<pb facs="tcp:103829:3"/> 
               <hi>Paul's;</hi> in which, as I did not deſire to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe any,</hi> ſo neither did I hope to <hi>pleaſe all,</hi> whilſt in the proſecution and diſcharge of my duty, I was to concern my ſelf in the faults of the <hi>preſent,</hi> to counter-argue a <hi>profitable vice,</hi> and ſo could expect no leſs than <hi>their diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> to whom the over-ruling ſentence of a <hi>guilty conſcience</hi> ſhould apply that <hi>hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of my Text. The Treaſure which I covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was not their <hi>favour,</hi> but <hi>amendment,</hi> and therefore if I <hi>lanc'd</hi> them to the <hi>quick,</hi> it was <hi>no more</hi> than I intended, and I am <hi>glad</hi> to be <hi>aſſur'd</hi> of it, though by their <hi>diſpleaſure;</hi> which whilſt I have gain'd from ſome of <hi>more note</hi> in the City than to be affronted by a careleſs <hi>contempt of their cenſures,</hi> (by whom I have been traduc'd for <hi>libelling</hi> Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, for ſuch vices of which they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>ſuſpected</hi> but <hi>by me</hi>) I muſt either by a <hi>paſſive ſilence</hi> bear falſe witneſs againſt my ſelf, and wilfully betray my own innocence, which were a ſin againſt my duty; or elſe to <hi>right</hi> my ſelf, and <hi>benefit</hi> them, <hi>appeal to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of more impartial judgments, who may beſt diſcern whether the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>weakneſs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:103829:3"/> which hath been betrayed were theirs or mine.</p>
            <p>If I had <hi>no relation</hi> to the City but <hi>by the Honour</hi> which I have had to <hi>relate</hi> to <hi>your ſelf,</hi> I ought <hi>for your ſake</hi> to have a <hi>better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion</hi> of it, than to lye under the leaſt <hi>tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of defaming</hi> it; which that I <hi>have not done</hi> at any time, much leſs at <hi>this,</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to them, who after the peruſal of this Sermon ſhall conſider, whether there be not men in the City who <hi>came as ill by their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,</hi> and make <hi>as bad uſe of their riches;</hi> as any I here deſcribe? and whether they ought in <hi>charity</hi> to conceive, I mean <hi>any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> than <hi>thoſe</hi> when I cenſure them? and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as they are,</hi> whether they can <hi>deſerve leſs?</hi> and if <hi>they</hi> who undertake to <hi>judge</hi> me, be <hi>none</hi> of them themſelves, why they ſhould <hi>partake of others ſins,</hi> by diſallowing of their deſerved <hi>reproof?</hi> whether I had better ſtrive to <hi>pleaſe</hi> or <hi>profit?</hi> to gain mens affections by <hi>doing</hi> my duty, or by <hi>omitting</hi> it? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I could have evidenc'd a greater reſpect to their <hi>perſons</hi> than by reprehending their <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which <hi>whereſoever</hi> I find I am bound to <hi>hate,</hi> but <hi>moſt</hi> in my <hi>beſt friends,</hi> to whom I
<pb facs="tcp:103829:4"/> 
               <hi>chiefly</hi> owe <hi>that degree</hi> of charity? I am apt to flatter my ſelf into a belief, that <hi>ſuch conſiderations as theſe</hi> may ſave me the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of an <hi>Apology,</hi> and prevail with ſuch <hi>ſincere lovers</hi> of <hi>plain dealing</hi> as <hi>your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> to <hi>judge charitably</hi> of what I now hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly recommend to your <hi>Patronage</hi> of which as I have <hi>formerly</hi> found the <hi>benefit,</hi> ſo I have <hi>ſtill</hi> reaſon to be the <hi>more ambitious,</hi> becauſe there is a power in <hi>your judgment</hi> to oblige <hi>others</hi> to have a <hi>better opinion</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged ſervant <hi>Tho: Cartwright.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barking</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103829:4"/>
            <head>The Danger of Riches.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Matthew the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> v. 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And again I ſay unto you, It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a Needle, than for a rich man to enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very much afraid that <hi>the firſt ſound</hi> of theſe words, may have poſſeſt you with a <hi>timerous expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation,</hi> of a <hi>lowd invective</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your <hi>great Diana</hi> of <hi>Worldly gain;</hi> and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently your <hi>prejudice</hi> may like a <hi>Sullen Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> have <hi>bar'd up</hi> your ears and hearts againſt both the <hi>Preacher</hi> and the <hi>Sermon:</hi> But yet, that I may be faithful to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> I muſt venture the <hi>loſs</hi> of your <hi>good opinion,</hi> to be <hi>inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> to the <hi>ſaving</hi> of <hi>your ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wiſh it were <hi>uncharitable</hi> to ſuppoſe, that there were <hi>any</hi> in this Congregation, of the <hi>ſame temper</hi> with the <hi>young man</hi> in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who could be content to <hi>keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> as long as they might <hi>keep their moneys,</hi> with whom <hi>as much Religion</hi> would go down as will <hi>advance</hi> their Trade, and who could pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103829:5"/> hear of <hi>glorifying God,</hi> till we come to tell them that they muſt do it <hi>with their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> But when <hi>Godlineſs</hi> begins to <hi>incroach</hi> on <hi>their gain,</hi> they care not <hi>how little</hi> they have to do with it; they then conclude it high time with <hi>Demas</hi> to <hi>forſake St. Paul,</hi> to <hi>embrace this preſent world,</hi> and to give the Devil his demands, <hi>fall down and worſhip him,</hi> rather than go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Omnia haec,</hi> all theſe things.</p>
               <p>If this be <hi>your unhappy temper,</hi> I am fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed on a <hi>thankleſs argument,</hi> and ſuch as I am affraid you'l <hi>explode</hi> for an <hi>Heretical Doctrine,</hi> but yet I muſt not <hi>retract</hi> it, having no leſs than <hi>the authority of Heaven</hi> to confirm it.</p>
               <p>Nor do I think it <hi>the leſs ſeaſonable</hi> to inſiſt on the <hi>danger of Riches,</hi> becauſe you ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally complain of <hi>the want</hi> of them, but rather <hi>the more,</hi> that ſo I may turn <hi>your complaint</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>comfort,</hi> and teach you to <hi>applaud</hi> (upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts) what you now perhaps unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly <hi>bewail,</hi> I am come to <hi>congratulate</hi> them who have ſuch <hi>rubs</hi> as theſe <hi>removed out of their way</hi> to happineſs, and to rejoyce with them that the <hi>bunch of the Camel</hi> is taken off, to <hi>facilitate</hi> their paſſage through <hi>the eye of the needle;</hi> and to let them know that this will not anſwer <hi>the providence of God</hi> by <hi>grumbling</hi> at the eaſe which <hi>he</hi> hath given them, but by expreſſing their <hi>thankfulneſs</hi> for that he hath <hi>pluckt</hi> theſe <hi>thorns</hi> out of ther ſides.</p>
               <p>So that whether <hi>your conditions</hi> give you oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to uſe more <hi>moderation</hi> or <hi>patience,</hi> I may very pardonably entertain you with a diſcourſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103829:5"/> of the <hi>danger of Riches;</hi> the inordinate <hi>love</hi> whereof is the <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prima pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinos obſcaena pecunia mores intulit, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi fregerunt ſecula luxu Divitiae mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>original</hi> of moſt of your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages.</p>
               <p>We find (verſe 16.) a <hi>young man</hi> ſtarting a very <hi>important Quaere</hi> to our Saviour, <hi>What good thing he ſhould do to make him capable of eternal happineſs:</hi> whereupon our Saviour refers him to <hi>the keeping of the Commandments</hi> (verſe 17) He inſtantly replyed that he had gone as far as that already, having all his time been a <hi>conſtant obſerver of the Law.</hi> (verſe 20.) Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour approving theſe gracious beginnings in him, ſpeaks kindly to him and endeavours to win him to <hi>that degree of contempt of worldly Riches</hi> which might give him the <hi>advantages</hi> of relieving and ſupporting others, and thereby <hi>qualify</hi> him for a <hi>capacity</hi> of being a <hi>true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in the Church <hi>militant,</hi> and <hi>a Saint</hi> in the <hi>triumphant:</hi> He tels him that <hi>he muſt,</hi> upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the reward laid up in heaven, <hi>be content to part with all</hi> the wealth of the world, <hi>whenſoever</hi> it ſhall be <hi>required</hi> of him, either <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</hi> or <hi>by conſequence,</hi> when he cannot obey any <hi>particular precept</hi> without danger of being undone by it, which when the <hi>young man</hi> heard <hi>he went away ſorrowful,</hi> having a great eſtate, and not being willing <hi>to pay ſo dear</hi> for perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as <hi>to part with that</hi> to purchaſe it. (verſe 22.) Our Saviour obſerving his carriage, doth thereby convince his Diſciples <hi>how very hard a thing it is</hi> for a <hi>worldly minded</hi> man to become a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> (verſe 23.) and that others might not <hi>cheat</hi> their ſouls, as <hi>he</hi> for ſome time had done,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103829:6"/> with <hi>falſe pretentions</hi> to Heaven, and upon <hi>ſuch ſlight grounds</hi> arrive at ſo <hi>great a confidence,</hi> what he had before proved by that <hi>example,</hi> he now explains by a <hi>ſimilitude,</hi> where a <hi>rich man</hi> is compared to a <hi>Camel,</hi> and <hi>the Kingdome of God</hi> to the <hi>Eye of a needle,</hi> and our Saviour <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively declares,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> muſt part with <hi>as much</hi> of his humour before he can be capable of being a Chriſtian, as <hi>that beaſt</hi> muſt of <hi>its bulk</hi> to be qualifyed to paſs through ſo ſtreit a paſſage as is <hi>the eye of a needle:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which words we have
<list>
                     <item>1. The depoſition or truth to be believed, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>'tis eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Affidavit</hi> or authority which is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to vouch it. <hi>And again I ſay unto you.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>1. As to the Depoſition, we muſt remember that 'twas an ordinary <hi>Proverb</hi> among the <hi>Jews, Hebrews</hi> and <hi>Arabs, An Elephant can not paſs through the eye of a needle,</hi> to ſignify the moſt impoſſible thing: This proverb Chriſt was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to change, from the <hi>Elephant</hi> (a beaſt which few of his Auditors had ſeen) to a <hi>Camel,</hi> which was very ordinary in <hi>Syria,</hi> whoſe <hi>bunch on his back</hi> would hinder his paſſage through any <hi>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> entrance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophylact</hi> and <hi>Phavorinus</hi> will have it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred a <hi>Cable</hi> with which Mariners uſe to caſt their Anchors, and that which they phanſy to be <hi>more agreeable</hi> to the <hi>eye of a needle:</hi> but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103829:6"/> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> confeſſeth <hi>Suidas</hi> to be the firſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Author in whom he found <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſed for a <hi>Cable</hi> (and after him <hi>Camers;</hi>) and obſerving that <hi>Julius Pollux</hi> makes no mention of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the tacklings of a Ship, he rejects it as a <hi>Grammarian conjecture,</hi> and an interpretation of more <hi>boldneſs</hi> than <hi>authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>ſuch,</hi> as I conceive, or <hi>little better,</hi> is that other aſſertion which the <hi>Poſtillers</hi> make fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent uſe of, that there was a <hi>Gate in Jeruſalem</hi> call'd the <hi>Needle,</hi> through which it was not <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible</hi> but <hi>difficult</hi> for a Camel to paſs.</p>
               <p>The very <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of riches makes the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage <hi>difficult,</hi> and gives us cauſe to cry out <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, how hard it is? but the <hi>inordinate love of them</hi> renders it <hi>impoſſible;</hi> ſo that if by a <hi>rich man</hi> we underſtand one <hi>who truſts</hi> in his <hi>riches,</hi> (as the generality of them do) then it will come to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, How impoſſible it is? and ſo the <hi>ſimile</hi> of a <hi>Camel</hi> and a <hi>needles eye</hi> will fit it.</p>
               <p>Nor dare I tread <hi>ſo near</hi> upon the borders of <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> as to venture to ſay, that <hi>Our Saviour</hi> ever ſpake any thing by an <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> ſuch <hi>raſh expreſſions</hi> arguing <hi>groſs miſtakes,</hi> being by no means chargeable on the <hi>infinite knowledge</hi> of our Redeemer.</p>
               <p>Nor yet have I any temptation to deny, but that <hi>ſome great and rich men,</hi> who have been ſometimes <hi>on earth,</hi> are now <hi>great Saints</hi> in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and that there is <hi>ſtill room</hi> for many more; for God can <hi>untwiſt</hi> thoſe <hi>cords of vanity</hi> and <hi>cart-ropes of iniquity,</hi> with which the worldlings
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103829:7"/> are <hi>bound</hi> to their riches, and make them, as he did <hi>Matthew the Publican,</hi> paſs through the <hi>eye of a needle;</hi> and as <hi>Zacheus</hi> notwithſtanding his <hi>Camels back,</hi> his prodigious wealth, to paſs through that <hi>ſtreit gate</hi> which gives entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal life.</p>
               <p>But let me withal requeſt you to remember that ſuch <hi>miracles</hi> as theſe were the <hi>rarities</hi> and <hi>reſerves</hi> of heaven, and ſuch as are <hi>not often</hi> ſeen; it is very <hi>ſeldom</hi> that men are <hi>imparadiſ'd</hi> in this life and <hi>enthron'd</hi> in the next, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſidering the incomparable danger which they are in, <hi>Rich men</hi> had need have many a <hi>charge</hi> given them <hi>above others,</hi> to take care of their ſouls, leſt valuing their <hi>coyn</hi> above their <hi>conſcience,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>by their love to the world, and the things that are in the world;</hi> it appears that <hi>the love of the Father is not in them, Whoſoever will be a friend of the world is the enemy of God</hi> (ſays <hi>Saint James,</hi>) <note place="margin">Jam. 4.4.</note> and therefore hath little reaſon to expect a <hi>Kingdom from him:</hi> And that they might not <hi>flatter themſelves</hi> into a <hi>better opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of their condition than it <hi>deſerves,</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tels them in my Text, that <hi>it will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which <hi>truth</hi> though it have a ſufficient <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit</hi> to back it, even <hi>him</hi> in whoſe diſpoſal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone the Kingdom is, to confirm it; yet becauſe I am ſpeaking to <hi>Citizens,</hi> who will hardly think any <hi>ſecurity ſufficient</hi> when we are about to perſwade them <hi>out of their profit,</hi> whoſe <hi>faith</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103829:7"/> is not <hi>eaſily</hi> tempted to aſſent to any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>intereſt,</hi> I ſhall add to the <hi>teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> which you have had from heaven, the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> upon which the <hi>difficulty</hi> is grounded, that ſo the <hi>truth</hi> of the doctrine may not hereafter be <hi>diſputed,</hi> nor <hi>you</hi> need a <hi>ſecond lecture</hi> of faith in this particular: now theſe are to be drawn either from <hi>the ſtreitneſs of the way it ſelf,</hi> or from <hi>his incapacity more than other men to paſs it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not <hi>every man</hi> who is preſently <hi>capable</hi> of the Kingdom of God, much leſs a <hi>Rich man,</hi> which <hi>incapacity</hi> proceeds, not from the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of riches</hi> in themſelves, but from <hi>his prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to abuſe them,</hi> ſo far as to make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to his own damnation, which they <hi>will be</hi> if he either <hi>come wrongfully</hi> by them, or if <hi>juſtly</hi> and be not <hi>thankful</hi> for them, not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> with them, not careful to <hi>employ</hi> them to the <hi>ends</hi> for which they were given him; <hi>too confident</hi> in them, <hi>too regardleſs</hi> of <hi>the</hi> tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the devil lies under them to ſeduce and inſnare him, <hi>not willing to part with</hi> them as <hi>luggage</hi> when they hinder him, or throw them <hi>overboard</hi> as too much <hi>lading</hi> when they are ready to ſink him, but ſuffering them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intention of the Donor, to <hi>ſteal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his heart,</hi> and ingroſs his affections wholly to themſelves, ſo as that he <hi>ſeldom thinks</hi> of the Kingdom of God, <hi>alwaies undervalues</hi> it, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver really deſires it:</hi> for <hi>each</hi> of which, when I ſhall have produc'd a <hi>particular evidence,</hi> I will not be ſo uncharitable to <hi>you,</hi> whatſoever you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103829:8"/> mean to be to <hi>your ſelves,</hi> as to <hi>doubt</hi> but that <hi>this doctrine</hi> will go down for a <hi>truth</hi> with you, and be eaſily <hi>digeſted</hi> into ſuch a <hi>practical un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing</hi> of theſe periſhing riches as may be fit for <hi>me</hi> to recommend to you, in order to the ſalvation of your immortal ſouls: to each of which, with your <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>pardon</hi> I ſhall crave to ſpeak ſomthing, <hi>orderly, briefly</hi> and <hi>plainly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now firſt the paſſage into the Kingdom of God, may well be compared, as it is, to <hi>the eye of a needle,</hi> and term'd not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a broad way,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a way <hi>ful of thorns, and beſet with diffculties,</hi> which the <hi>looſe livers</hi> of the world do <hi>practically confeſs,</hi> whilſt with a <hi>loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering formality</hi> they ſtrive to avoid it.</p>
               <p>'Tis no ſuch eaſie matter for a man to have his <hi>converſation in Heaven</hi> whilſt he walks on earth, to enjoy God in the Creation and to paſs out of the <hi>ſenſible</hi> world into the <hi>intellectual,</hi> to live <hi>above the world</hi> and <hi>himſelf,</hi> and not to <hi>debaſe</hi> his ſoul in purſuit of <hi>low</hi> and particular ends and intereſts; to live <hi>in it,</hi> and not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted <hi>with it, as having all things, and yet poſſeſſing nothing;</hi> to carry himſelf <hi>above all</hi> that the world can do <hi>for</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> him, to bid <hi>defiance</hi> to <hi>all</hi> the powers of darkneſs ſo as not to <hi>ſhrink</hi> at any danger, not be <hi>diſhartned</hi> at any oppoſition of the enemy, to <hi>balk</hi> all the flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>temptations</hi> with which he would inveagle us, to <hi>row againſt the ſtream</hi> of the world and <hi>our own</hi> natural inclinations, to <hi>maſter</hi> our head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong affections with ſo <hi>ſtreit a rein,</hi> and to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103829:8"/> 
                  <hi>break</hi> them with ſo ſevere a Diſcipline that they run not away with us; to have our <hi>reaſon</hi> capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated to our <hi>Faith,</hi> our <hi>Will</hi> to our reaſon, and our <hi>affections</hi> to both: not to remember our <hi>darling ſins</hi> without <hi>grief and diſdain,</hi> nay not without <hi>hatred</hi> of our ſelves for having ever committed and embrac'd them; by mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſelf-denyal to <hi>pluck out our right eye leſt it offend us for the future,</hi> and never give over contending, till we have deſtroy'd the <hi>whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Sin;</hi> to love <hi>all good</hi> according to the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of its eminency, God <hi>above</hi> all, and others <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi> as they partake of his goodneſs, not to be <hi>overſway'd</hi> by any <hi>prevailing luſt,</hi> but to bring our <hi>inward Man</hi> into Obedience to the law; duly to <hi>obſerve</hi> and <hi>attend</hi> upon Divine Providence, and to bring <hi>our ſelves</hi> and all our <hi>actions</hi> into a complyance with Gods will, <hi>Quis ad haec idoneus? Lord who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> and yet <hi>this</hi> and <hi>no wider</hi> is the way to Heaven, into which if <hi>many ſtrive to enter and ſhall not be able,</hi> what will become of them who never make it their buſineſs to regard it? <hi>if the Righteous ſcarcely be ſav'd, where ſhall the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and the unjuſt appear?</hi> it is beyond my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to give them any more comfort than St. <hi>James</hi> hath done; <note place="margin">S. James 1.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 5.1</note> 
                  <hi>Go to now, ye Rich Men, weep and howle for your miſeries which ſhall come upon you, ye have liv'd in pleaſure on the Earth and been wanton, ye have nouriſh'd your hearts as in a day of ſlaughter;</hi> and the <hi>entrance</hi> into the Kingdom of God being ſo <hi>ſtreit, you,</hi> of all Men are leaſt likely to paſs it, as will appear,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103829:9"/>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> A natura &amp; ingenio divitis.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The ſimile of a <hi>Camel</hi> and <hi>the eye of a needle</hi> are exactly <hi>proportion'd</hi> to the Salvation of a Rich Man who is <hi>incapable</hi> of it; without a <hi>more miraculous extenſion</hi> of the mercy of his Maker than is by himſelf known to <hi>ſuffice</hi> ſuch as have not been <hi>condemned</hi> to ſo much Worldly plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. His <hi>truſts, joyes,</hi> and <hi>confidences</hi> are ſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to a Chriſtian, and ſo perfectly <hi>irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> with them, that there muſt be an <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hand</hi> of God in the way of converting Grace to make <hi>him</hi> who ſo excells in the gifts of Fortune, to <hi>deny all and become nothing for Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Rich</hi> are apt to be <hi>more in love</hi> with the World than <hi>other</hi> Men, and ſo many are the noyſom <hi>weeds</hi> which grow out of ſuch <hi>fat ſoyls,</hi> that 'tis very diſputable whether they who are alwaies penuriouſly <hi>brooding over</hi> their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are ever guilty of doing any thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable but <hi>but when they dye,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Avarus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi cum moritur nil recte fecit.</hi> Seneca.</note> who <hi>whilſt they live,</hi> are good to <hi>none,</hi> but worſt to <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Avarus nemini bonus, ſibi peſſimus,</hi> Sen.</note> the more <hi>rich</hi> they are, commonly the leſs <hi>Righteous, Goods and Goodneſs</hi> being no intimate acquaintance. <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Raro ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul hominibus bona fortuna bonaque mens datur.</hi> Liv.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>large Fortune</hi> and a <hi>narrow Soul</hi> are ſuch great <hi>Comrades,</hi> that <hi>Plato</hi> would not allow it poſſible for them to be parted. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and therefore of <hi>all</hi> vices that of <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> as it comes near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. So it was <hi>never charg'd</hi> upon any of Gods Children in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, of <hi>all</hi> who came to Chriſt, only
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103829:9"/> 
                  <hi>Judas</hi> the <hi>Son of perdition</hi> is branded with it, who was therefore thought fit to have the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>bag.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor would I be thought to concluded that this <hi>incapacity</hi> of theirs proceeds from <hi>the nature of riches</hi> in themſelves, which that they might not be diſpos'd as <hi>evils</hi> are ſometimes given to <hi>good men,</hi> &amp; that they might not be <hi>eſteem'd</hi> as the <hi>beſt things</hi> are more <hi>frequently</hi> beſtow'd on the <hi>worſt.</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne puten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur malae dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; bonis, &amp; ne putentur ſumma bona dantur &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi> Aug. Ep. 7. ad Bonif.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But I think I preach to <hi>them</hi> who will ſooner turn any thing than <hi>Stoicks,</hi> and therefore I ſhall not trouble <hi>you</hi> nor <hi>my ſelf</hi> to bring Riches in more credit with you, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> for fear you have already a better opinion of them than they deſerve. They may be <hi>good Servants</hi> but they muſt be <hi>bad Maſters;</hi> they are neither <hi>abſolutely good</hi> in themſelves, nor <hi>infallible Teſtimonies</hi> of Gods favour: 'tis for the moſt part a <hi>labour</hi> to get them and a <hi>load</hi> to keep them, and that the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier,</hi> becauſe we may neither be the <hi>better</hi> with them, nor the <hi>worſe</hi> without them, ſince the <hi>beſt</hi> advantages of which they can boaſt are but thoſe of an <hi>inſtrument,</hi> which has but an <hi>inferior, ſubordinate</hi> and <hi>ſerviceable,</hi> even the <hi>loweſt degree of goodneſs</hi> that can be, and yet are <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times</hi> unſerviceable, and uſeleſs for <hi>that</hi> too, whilſt they <hi>ſeem to be</hi> what they are not, <hi>boaſt of</hi> what they have not, and <hi>promiſe</hi> what they cannot perform, and ſo not only <hi>periſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> but make their <hi>Poſſeſſers periſh with them,</hi> which they will infallibly do,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If they come <hi>wrongfully</hi> by them. God hath <hi>lockt</hi> up Gold and Silver in the <hi>ſecret Mines</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103829:10"/> and Caverns of the Earth, and yet though they are plac'd <hi>under foot,</hi> Men will not <hi>overlook</hi> them, but rend open the Bowels of the Earth in a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution <hi>by any means</hi> to obtain them, though in the <hi>ſearch</hi> after them they loſe both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>themſelves;</hi> and well might they therefore be call'd <hi>Thorns,</hi> as things for which they do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <hi>ſmart</hi> who lay their hands on them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis ſimul viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is incubat.</hi>
                  </note> Sin is ſo commonly the <hi>Rich</hi> Mans <hi>Factor,</hi> who rarely ſcruples <hi>any</hi> wicked action, if it bring in a conſiderable <hi>advantage,</hi> that the <hi>Proverb</hi> takes notice of it, <hi>Dives aut iniquus eſt aut ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui haeres,</hi> and we have one in plain Engliſh which intimates no leſs ſaying, <hi>Happy is thnt Child whoſe Father goes to the Divel,</hi> and ſo in earneſt it is much to be fear'd <hi>they</hi> do, who <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage</hi> their Souls to the Divel for a little <hi>preſent profit,</hi> and will not <hi>regard</hi> till they cannot <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover</hi> them.</p>
               <p>They who <hi>get</hi> or <hi>increaſe</hi> their Eſtates by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding</hi> in matter of <hi>truſt</hi> or <hi>traffick, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, lying, foreſwaring, bribing, oppreſſing, exacting, uſery, theft, witholding their dues, Sacriledge,</hi> or by the <hi>faſhionable way of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> when they have feather'd their Neaſts with other Mens Eſtates, and can cheat them into a ſlender Compoſition, or by <hi>taking advantage</hi> of the buyers <hi>ignorance, indiſcretion</hi> or <hi>neceſſity,</hi> (and I muſt ſtill put an, &amp;c. to the end of it, whilſt I am ſpeaking of a <hi>myſtery</hi> in which <hi>ſome</hi> of this Auditory may poſſibly be <hi>ſo well vers'd,</hi> as ſecretly to accuſe me for want of a <hi>ſufficient enumeration</hi>) in <hi>all</hi> which wayes they do more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103829:10"/> 
                  <hi>over-reach themſelves</hi> than <hi>thoſe</hi> with whom they deal, whilſt by theſe <hi>very acts</hi> they <hi>ſell</hi> their ſouls to the Devil and take that <hi>unjuſt gain</hi> for the payment: I ſay they who have practic'd any of theſe unlawful waies of getting or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing their eſtates, muſt firſt make <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the parties wronged, before they can hope to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Now then, <hi>you</hi> are beſt able to conſider <hi>how hard</hi> it will be for them who have gone on in ſuch courſes, to call to mind <hi>how many, how much,</hi> and <hi>how often</hi> they have deceived; and how much <hi>harder</hi> it will be to <hi>find</hi> out <hi>them</hi> or <hi>their heirs</hi> to whom to make <hi>reſtitution,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which their Repentance will never avail them. Examine <hi>your conſciences</hi> and let <hi>them</hi> reſolve you of this difficulty, <hi>for your ſakes</hi> I tremble to think on it.</p>
               <p>If all of you come juſtly by your riches, (which all your acquaintance are not bound to believe) yet a <hi>Camel' may eaſier paſs through the eye of a needle, than you into the Kingdom of God,</hi> if you are not <hi>thankfull</hi> for them to him who has bleſt you with them, according to the meaſure of your enjoyments; this being a <hi>debt</hi> wherein you ſtand bound to him for <hi>the free uſe of his creatures.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.4.</note> Now rich men <hi>owe more</hi> in this ſence to God, than other men, and if it ſhall appear that they <hi>pay leſs,</hi> their very enjoyments will riſe up in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them. Wo be unto us if <hi>the more</hi> God in mercy remembers us, <hi>the ſooner</hi> we forget both <hi>him</hi> and <hi>our ſelves. Iſrael</hi> were no ſooner poſſeſt of the <hi>promiſed land</hi> but they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103829:11"/> grew <hi>diſobedient;</hi> fulneſs bred <hi>ſecurity,</hi> ſecurity brought forth <hi>negligence,</hi> and that the contempt of their Benefactors, and I wiſh this be not a <hi>catching diſeaſe</hi> amongſt us likewiſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They who are <hi>not content</hi> with their rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es can never be <hi>ſav'd</hi> with them, when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they <hi>debauch</hi> mens minds, and work them to a kind of <hi>inſatiableneſs,</hi> ſo that their ſouls are alwaies <hi>in travel</hi> under the <hi>pangs,</hi> and <hi>throws</hi> of a ſolicitous purſuit of <hi>more gain,</hi> they give them <hi>an earneſt</hi> of eternal torments in this life, <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Avaro ſe ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil deſiderare poſſe pernicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius quam ut longum vivat</hi> Sen.</note> and an <hi>infallible aſſurance</hi> of the arrears in the next. How uſual is it for rich men to covet <hi>more than they have</hi> with ſuch <hi>intemperance,</hi> as to forget their <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> and be ſick for what <hi>they have not?</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quod habet numerat tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod non non habet, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</hi> Manil. Eſa. 5.3. Hab. 2.5.</note> How frequently doth the <hi>deſire</hi> of wealth, after it once exceeds its lawful bounds, become as inſatiable as Hell, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no ſtint or period of growth? <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Creſit amor nummi, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ipſa pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia creſcit.</hi> Juv.</note> And how much <hi>diſcontent</hi> do they generally betray, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>fear of loſing</hi> what they have, or the <hi>feaveriſh deſire</hi> of graſping more, inſomuch as that they <hi>tug</hi> at the <hi>world</hi> as at a <hi>narrow ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-cloath,</hi> where none thinks he hath <hi>enough</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he get <hi>all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That which renders rich mens paſſage into the Kingdom of God the more difficult is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>ſeldom uſe or beſtow their riches, to that end for which they are given them. Qui bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis abundat bonum eſſe oportet.</hi> Great <hi>Accounts</hi> muſt have great <hi>Audits,</hi> and the more <hi>plentiful</hi> the entertainment hath been, the <hi>larger</hi> will be the reckoning. <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ingentia be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificia, ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia vitia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicia.</hi>
                  </note> Great benefits anſwered with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103829:11"/> great ſins, will be attended with fearful judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Now God gives men <hi>wealth</hi> not as to <hi>Treaſurers,</hi> but <hi>Stewards,</hi> not for their <hi>own uſes,</hi> but <hi>his ſervice,</hi> and he gives the poor many <hi>bils of Aſſignment</hi> on their plenty, whereupon this muſt either <hi>burden</hi> their conſciences, or <hi>lighten</hi> their purſes, and expect to be ſummon'd to a <hi>Redde rationem,</hi> to give an account of their <hi>Stewardſhip:</hi> If therefore your <hi>love of riches</hi> hath ſtrangled your <hi>love of God</hi> and <hi>your neighbour,</hi> 
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non diligit proximum qui diligit durum</hi> Chryſ.</note> ſo that you regard <hi>neither</hi> in the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, but <hi>defeat</hi> the <hi>main end</hi> of your receipts, how dreadful will your guilt be, and how deſperate your condition?</p>
               <p n="5">5. If in times of difficulty and diſtreſs you place more <hi>confidence in your money</hi> than <hi>your Maker,</hi> it will infallibly deſtroy you. If you ſet your hearts upon your riches, place your contentment in them, and reckon them as your <hi>beſt friends</hi> in time of need, you make <hi>them your Idols,</hi> and <hi>God himſelf</hi> but a <hi>puny</hi> to the work of his <hi>own</hi> hands. Now how doth the <hi>Omnipotency of money</hi> make all people proſtrate themſelves to it, and worſhip it? <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.6. Pſal. 52.2.</note> and how apt are they <hi>who have riches</hi> to <hi>place</hi> their confidence in them as their greateſt happineſs? to <hi>truſt in their wealth, and boaſt themſelves in the multitude of their riches,</hi> and how eaſily they'l forget <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>their friends,</hi> and grow <hi>proud</hi> 
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi uber ibi tuber.</hi> Apul.</note> of their plenty, as if it would <hi>privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> them in any villany <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Potentia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitis quaſi jus, quoddam ad delinquendum eſt, privilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um poteſtatis eſt, non tantum inpunè ſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam juſtè de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquere.</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lad.</note> will be no news to tell you.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103829:12"/>
               <p>There is ſuch an <hi>inchantment in wealth</hi> that it perſwades men to ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> to their ſouls, and to <hi>rock</hi> them aſleep in the <hi>cradle</hi> of ſecurity, as if it were able both <hi>to give them</hi> true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and to <hi>continue</hi> it; and therefore <hi>Saint Paul</hi> bids us <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>charge them who are rich in this world that they be not high-minded, nor truſt in their uncertain riches, but in the living God who gives us richly all things to enjoy;</hi> &amp; indeed they have too much need of ſuch caution, for they are apt to turn profeſt <hi>Independants,</hi> in a conceit of their own <hi>ſelf-ſufficiency,</hi> to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves inſenſible of their dependance on God, like the <hi>Prodigal</hi> when he had got his <hi>portion</hi> out of his Fathers hands, to take their leave of him and <hi>ſet up</hi> for themſelves, <note place="margin">Job. 31.24.</note> 
                  <hi>to make gold their hope, and ſay unto the fine gold, thou art my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,</hi>whereas indeed they owe their <hi>ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial happineſs</hi> meerly to the deluſion of their phancy, nor have they any better pretence to it than that they have not ſenſe enough to know their miſery.</p>
               <p>For though the Divel like a <hi>cunning jugler</hi> as he is, have put the World like a <hi>piece of mony</hi> into their hands, and bids them <hi>hold faſt,</hi> yet he by his <hi>Leger-demain</hi> will quickly <hi>get it out</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and before they can <hi>open</hi> their <hi>hands</hi> and their <hi>eyes</hi> they many times find <hi>nothing</hi> but that they are <hi>cheated,</hi> viz. that their <hi>Riches</hi> have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Wings</hi> and are fled away from them. A Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal <hi>Son,</hi> an unfaithful <hi>Servant,</hi> an ill <hi>Debtor,</hi> a <hi>ſuit at</hi> Law, a <hi>fire</hi> by Land, or a <hi>ſtorm</hi> at Sea, may quickly impoveriſh you: But whilſt I preach
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103829:12"/> to Citizens who of late years have as oft <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried</hi> as their <hi>Wives,</hi> and to Merchants who <hi>ſink</hi> as faſt as their <hi>Veſſels,</hi> I muſt be ſo modeſt as to remember that you are better able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct <hi>me</hi> than I <hi>you</hi> in the uncertain and <hi>trickliſh tenure of Riches;</hi> and therefore I ſhall only beg that you would improve <hi>that part of your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> to abate <hi>part of your Confidence,</hi> with which you can no more enter into Heaven than can a <hi>Camel paſs through the eye of a Needle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. If you are too <hi>regardleſs of the temptations,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Magna il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecebra delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum affluentia.</hi> Ambr.</note> which the Divel hides under your Riches to ſeduce and inſnare you, (as Rich Men generally are) you can <hi>never enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> If you would deal impartially with your ſelves and not turn <hi>Traytors</hi> to your own Souls, I ſhould not need to tell you how many <hi>Vices</hi> are apt to be ingendred, and how many <hi>miſchiefs</hi> do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the care of <hi>getting,</hi> the deſire of <hi>keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the fear of <hi>loſing,</hi> and the grief <hi>for the loſs</hi> of Worldly Riches, in which reſpect they are term'd by St. <hi>Auguſt. Pericula poſſidentium pretioſiſſima, ſpecioſa ſupplicia, beneficia viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata:</hi> inſnaring courteſies; for the Divel is no ſuch frank Chapman as to ſell his wares for nothing.</p>
               <q>Munera magna quidem praebet, ſed praebet in hamo.</q>
               <p>Nor would the World like a <hi>cheating Gamſter</hi> ſuffer you to <hi>win at firſt,</hi> but with a deſign to tempt you <hi>to loſe all, and your ſelves at laſt,</hi> and therefore <hi>Agur</hi> was ſo ſhy of the World as to ſuſpect ſome charge in its kindneſs, <note place="margin">Prov. 30.8,9.</note> 
                  <hi>Give me not Riches, feed me with food convenient for me,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103829:13"/> leſt I be full and deny thee, and ſay, where is the Lord?</hi> and we are no ſooner taught by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to pray for <hi>our daily bread,</hi> but as ſoon as thoſe words are out of our mouth to pray for <hi>the forgiveneſs of our ſins;</hi> ſo apt are we to make the <hi>bleſſings of God</hi> inſtruments of <hi>Rebellion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, to inſlave <hi>our faith</hi> to our <hi>preſent enjoyments,</hi> and not ſuffer it to <hi>perfect its work in us,</hi> to turn Infidels, and reſolve to ſtop our <hi>ears</hi> and <hi>hearts</hi> againſt any Doctrine which makes <hi>againſt our profit;</hi> let the Goſpel ſay what it will, to allow it <hi>no more</hi> Faith than it will <hi>pay for,</hi> which was the reaſon why <hi>ſo few Rich Men</hi> were converted by our Saviour, and why his Miniſters cannot hope to prevail <hi>with many,</hi> becauſe what we proffer towards their conviction is like <hi>Lots Sermon</hi> to his Sons in Law concerning the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> they take us to be but <hi>in jeſt</hi> whem we declare againſt ſuch a <hi>thrifty vice,</hi> and will <hi>ſhut</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> and their <hi>purſes,</hi> charm we never ſo wiſely; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us with Tears, that they are flat Atheiſts, <note place="margin">3. Philip. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> and our Saviour paſſes an heavy doom upon them; <note place="margin">6 Math. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Wo be to them who are Rich, for ye have received your Conſolation,</hi> you have made a God of your Riches here
<q>(Jupiter eſt quodcunque cupis.)</q> and you muſt look for no Salvation but what they are able to <hi>purchaſe</hi> for you hereafter, and that eſpecially,</p>
               <p n="7">7. If you are <hi>not willing to part with them as luggage</hi> to quit your intereſt and claim in them at
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103829:13"/> the <hi>firſt call</hi> from God, and to diſpoſe of your ſelves and your Worldly enjoyments according to his pleaſure, without any reluctancy, they will render your entrance into the Kingdom of God impoſſible. <hi>No Man can ſerve two Maſters, God and Mammon,</hi> nor at once be the favorite of the <hi>Prince of light,</hi> and the <hi>Prince of this World;</hi> they therefore who divide themſelves between <hi>both</hi> are Servants of <hi>neither,</hi> and therefore this <hi>Young man</hi> was injoyn'd to <hi>forſake all before</hi> he undertook to <hi>follow Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have all a race to run, and <hi>Rich Men</hi> are like <hi>Tortoiſes,</hi> clog'd with ſuch a <hi>weighty ſhell,</hi> that they cannot draw it after them in any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of <hi>obtaining it:</hi> the Soul cannot <hi>mount</hi> to Heaven when it has ſuch a <hi>load</hi> as the <hi>World</hi> hanging on its wing: Too much <hi>lading</hi> is many times the cauſe why the <hi>Ship</hi> does ſink; and in a <hi>ſhort journey</hi> the <hi>more proviſion</hi> Travellers have, the greater reaſon do they find to <hi>complain</hi> of their <hi>Burden.</hi> A <hi>golden Apple</hi> does make Men ſtoop in their way towards Heaven, and like the <hi>fooliſh Virgins</hi> to tarry ſo long behind for it till they are ſhut out; and ſuch is the <hi>Genius of Rich Men,</hi> that they would be thought very <hi>greedy</hi> of Salvation, and yet like this <hi>young Man,</hi> when they are put to the proof they will part with nothing for it, and if they cannot have Chriſt upon <hi>their own terms,</hi> they will not take him upon <hi>his;</hi> and you may <hi>gueſs</hi> how paſſionately they are inamor'd with the world by their grief at the parting with it. <hi>Sine dolore amittitur, quod ſine amore poſſidetur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is it enough to part with Riches <hi>out of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103829:14"/> your hands</hi> unleſs it be <hi>out of your hearts too,</hi> for 'tis leſs maſtery to forſake <hi>Worldly Riches</hi> than to forſake <hi>the love of them.</hi> If we diſquiet our hearts with a deſire of any Earthly thing which <hi>we have not,</hi> or are <hi>troubled</hi> at the loſs of what we <hi>would have again</hi> but <hi>cannot,</hi> as much <hi>ſorrow</hi> and <hi>unwillingneſs</hi> as we have in the <hi>loſing</hi> of them, ſo much <hi>affection</hi> we had for the <hi>keeping</hi> of them. As therefore you ever hope for the Kingdom of God, you muſt part with all <hi>in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> though not alwaies <hi>in poſſeſſion,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivet</hi> your hearts from the World, and not <hi>hoard up</hi> and <hi>with-hold</hi> the things thereof from a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Communication, but alwaies in <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and preparation of mind</hi> to be ready to <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render</hi> them, and that <hi>actually</hi> too, when the <hi>Church</hi> ſtands in need of them, and therefore the <note place="margin">Hebr. 10.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Saints took joyfully the ſpoyling of their goods, knowing in themſelves that they have in Heaven a better and induring Substance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. If you ſuffer them <hi>to ſteal away your hearts,</hi> and <hi>ingroſs</hi> your affections wholly to themſelves, a <hi>Camel may as eaſily go through the eye of a nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle as you ſhall enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> He who ever hopes to be ſav'd, muſt reckon his <hi>beſt affections</hi> and deſigns, as <hi>too choice</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious a <hi>treaſure</hi> to be prodigally <hi>ſquandred</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon ſuch <hi>ſorry trifles</hi> as <hi>riches</hi> are. He muſt not make his heart the <hi>worlds Warehouſe,</hi> when he hath once conſecrated it as a <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>the Holy-Ghoſt.</hi> A true Chriſtian will never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſuch an <hi>incurvation</hi> of his immortal ſoul,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103829:14"/> to things ſo much <hi>below</hi> him, as to love the world <hi>againſt</hi> God, or <hi>more</hi> than him, or <hi>equal</hi> to him, or <hi>diſtinctly</hi> from him, but only in a <hi>ſubordination</hi> to him, as being truly ſenſible that what affection ſoever the world wins of him is loſt to God.</p>
               <p>And, Lord, <hi>how few</hi> rich men are of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, who think <hi>ſo highly</hi> of their Riches, and act ſo <hi>vigorouſly for them</hi> as if their <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>they</hi> were of equal <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eodem ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio ſervatur nummus &amp; animus.</hi>
                  </note> concernment? How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably do they <hi>degrade</hi> their ſouls in force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to <hi>take</hi> up their happineſs amongſt ſuch <hi>periſhing</hi> enjoyments, and in bounding all their projects and deſigns within the compaſs of this earth which they bread upon?</p>
               <p>Can thoſe men ever hope to be <hi>heirs of Heaven,</hi> who are alwaies aiming at <hi>ends more ignoble</hi> than <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſhaping their mindes as much as may be into a <hi>conformity</hi> with <hi>that</hi> which they aim at, till they become as <hi>unſtable, inconſtant, perplext</hi> and <hi>tumultuous</hi> things, as the <hi>World</hi> it ſelf is? So much as their delight is in theſe <hi>tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory enjoyments,</hi> ſo much is abated of their <hi>delight in God,</hi> and whilſt they are ſo furiouſly <hi>driving on</hi> their thriving projects and deſigns of <hi>riſing</hi> in this world, they are <hi>turning their backs</hi> upon Chriſt, and <hi>poſting</hi> towards deſtruction.</p>
               <p>They who are <hi>mancipatipecuniis,</hi> ſuch drudges to their eſtates, as to ſuffer them to over-rule them, to ſuch hard conditions may be ſaid to <hi>have riches</hi> as a man <hi>has a fever,</hi> which may be more properly ſaid <hi>to have him under its tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Bion</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 4.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103829:15"/> in <hi>Laertius,</hi> he doth not <hi>poſſeſs</hi> his eſtate, but is <hi>poſſeſt by it,</hi> which if it be not the <hi>ſame</hi> is <hi>as bad</hi> as being <hi>poſſeſt by the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The love of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>world,</hi> are like <hi>fire and water</hi> which cannot conſiſt in <hi>intenſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</hi> but deſtroy each other, the <hi>more</hi> the heart gives place to the care of <hi>that,</hi> the <hi>leſs room</hi> doth it leave for the thoughts and remembrance of <hi>God.</hi> Riches have a <hi>pilphering quality</hi> whereby they ſteal away the love of the heart, ingroſſing it to themſelves, <hi>warping</hi> the conſcience, <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting</hi> the judgment, <hi>bribing</hi> it with a <hi>retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fee,</hi> beſpeaking it for themſelves, and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting</hi> our deſires from <hi>that end</hi> for which we ought to have deſired them, and therefore they who are thus <hi>cumbred</hi> and <hi>loaded</hi> with them, are in very ſmall likelihood of being <hi>Saints,</hi> Firſt,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>they ſeldom think of the Kingdom of God.</hi> Their minds are perpetually <hi>rambling</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, and they ſo deeply <hi>ingaged,</hi> and <hi>immerſt</hi> in the world, that they are unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the affairs of their own ſouls. All their rooms are <hi>throng'd</hi> with <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Creſcentem ſequitur cura pecuniam.</hi>
                  </note> cares and turbulent paſſions, that unleſs God will be crowded up with the world in ſo <hi>ſtreit a lodging</hi> he muſt not look for <hi>entertainment</hi> there. When they wax fat with the enjoyment of eaſe and plenty, they never think of another world, becauſe, they perceive the remembrance of it to <hi>allay</hi> their joy, and ſo they have neither <hi>leaſure, patience,</hi> nor <hi>diſcretion</hi> to mind it. They will not ſuffer ſuch <hi>troubleſome gueſts</hi> as are the <hi>thoughts of Heaven,</hi> to lodge long in their memories, but contrive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103829:15"/> how to put their doom out of their thoughts till they put themſelves into an incapacity of avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; ſo that</p>
               <p n="2">2. They <hi>alwaies undervalue the Kingdom of God,</hi> whilſt they make Godlineſs <hi>truckle</hi> under gain, and prefer riches <hi>above faith</hi> and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as the <hi>Gergeſens</hi> did their <hi>ſwine,</hi> before our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and as the <hi>cock in the fable</hi> did the grain of <hi>corn</hi> before the <hi>pearl of ineſtimable price</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod.</note> That which men value moſt they take greateſt care of, <hi>Majori bono debetur major amor,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who ſpend more time and care to <hi>ſecure their eſtates</hi> than their ſouls, do ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare upon which they place the greater eſtimate.</p>
               <p>To part with <hi>good things</hi> to get <hi>better</hi> you will allow, I am ſure, for a good piece of merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Magna amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere ut majora lucreris non eſt damnum ſed negotiatio.</hi> Bern.</note> and therefore if you had ſo good an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Heaven as it deſerves, you would <hi>lay up in ſtore for your ſelves a good foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time to come, that you might lay hold on eternal life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But alas! how ſeldom do rich men worſhip God ſincerely, unleſs he deſcend <hi>like Jupiter</hi> in a <hi>ſhowre of gold;</hi> or eſteem of any <hi>as worth</hi> their acquaintauce, <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quantum habes tantum vales.</hi>
                  </note> unleſs they be ſuch as they may probably get by; and then they are ſuch <hi>Jews</hi> that if a <hi>Calf</hi> be of <hi>Gold</hi> they <hi>will worſhip it,</hi> nay they would hardly deſire to <hi>live long themſelves,</hi> but that they may have their breath <hi>gratis</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>paying intereſt</hi> for it; if <hi>time</hi> ſhould turn <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> and charge his <hi>weekly revenues</hi> with an <hi>exciſe,</hi> they would hardly be at the <hi>expence</hi> of a longer life, whilſt <hi>death</hi> were to be had for <hi>little</hi> or <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103829:16"/> If Religion be ſo <hi>dear,</hi> as that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>kept</hi> without the diſtribution of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, <hi>as</hi> and <hi>when</hi> their brethren ſhall need them, 'tis no <hi>penny-worth</hi> for them; If <hi>God ſhall put forth his hand and touch their eſtates,</hi> the Devil (who knows their minds) will anſwer for them, that <hi>they ſhall curſe him to his face;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Job. 1.9.</note> who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what perpetual <hi>ſervice</hi> this temptation of <hi>riches</hi> did him, queſtioned not but that it would have <hi>overcome Job,</hi> and doubted whither our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> himſelf could withſtand it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Rich men <hi>do never really deſire the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> They ſpread their <hi>Sails</hi> to no <hi>wind</hi> that brings not in ſome preſent <hi>profit:</hi> and if they entertain Religion, 'tis often as a <hi>journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to bring in their gain, they'l keep it <hi>at an allowance</hi> to ſerve their <hi>turn,</hi> and at beſt they will but admit it as a <hi>Gueſt to take ſuch as it finds,</hi> and if once it take the freedom to <hi>find fault</hi> with their incomes, it muſt be packing. If it prove an enemy <hi>to</hi> and intercept them <hi>from</hi> the proſecution of their temporal <hi>ends,</hi> they will have nothing more to do with it.</p>
               <p>Their <hi>deſires</hi> which are both the trueſt <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of their <hi>preſent</hi> ſtate, and the ſureſt <hi>progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi> of their <hi>future,</hi> are never really ſet upon Heaven, <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui aliquid deſiderat, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat etiam id quod ſcit neceſſario inde ſubſecuturum.</hi> Medina. 1. 2. Qu. 5. Art. 8.</note> for if they did deſire <hi>the end,</hi> they muſt likewiſe deſire <hi>the way</hi> which alone can bring them to it, without which 'tis a <hi>roaving velleity</hi> ſhot at randome, and level'd at an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility; now <hi>this</hi> that they <hi>do not</hi> deſire hath been abundantly prov'd already, again, <hi>if they did</hi> deſire it, they would be <hi>ſick of the want of it,</hi> and reſtleſs till they had ſecur'd it. <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Quod arden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius deſideras, cares aegrius</hi> Bern. 51. Serm in Cant.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:103829:16"/>
               <p>Put all theſe together and let your own hearts be Judges, and declare whether a <hi>Camel may not as eaſily go through the eye of a needle, as a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> And that you may not think <hi>me</hi> either <hi>Magiſterial</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable,</hi> I ſhall requeſt you in the <hi>Spirit of meekneſs</hi> not to take <hi>my word</hi> for it, for I do not ſay it <hi>of my ſelf,</hi> but 'tis the <hi>decree of Heaven,</hi> as you ſhall ſee by</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>2. <hi>The Affidavit,</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> which is brought in the firſt words of my Text to vouch and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. A Doctrine which runs <hi>ſo croſs</hi> to the <hi>grain</hi> of the World, that we had need have <hi>Chriſts Authority</hi> for it, and his <hi>expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> to publiſh it, which we <hi>have</hi> in theſe words: <hi>And again I ſay unto you.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>hard</hi> ſaying, indeed and ſo much the <hi>harder,</hi> becauſe 'tis <hi>his</hi> who is a compleat Judge of it; one who can neither be <hi>deceiv'd himſelf,</hi> nor tempted <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us;</hi> the <hi>God of truth</hi> aſſerts it, and, <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Author, tanta fides.</hi> Who would have believ'd it, unleſs <hi>he</hi> had affirm'd it? and who dares di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt it now we have <hi>his word</hi> for it? If you ſtudyed our Saviours anſwer to <hi>Dives,</hi> you would think that he aſſign'd <hi>Heaven</hi> meerly for an <hi>inheritance</hi> of ſuch as wanted here, and <hi>Hell</hi> for thoſe who <hi>abounded;</hi> and as he denounc'd a <hi>Wo againſt them, Luke</hi> 6.24. ſo he forewarn'd his Diſciples of the difficulty of their Salvation, and when he perceiv'd them to be offended at what he had ſaid before, he repeats it <hi>higher</hi> in my Text, and gives them the <hi>meaſure</hi> of the difficulty by a <hi>ſimilitude;</hi> and certainly 'tis as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103829:17"/> difficult <hi>now</hi> as when he firſt affirm'd it.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Children of God</hi> in all ages have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd no leſs; hence was that ſtrange complaint of the <hi>Spouſe in the Canticles,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Can. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>my mothers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were angry with me, they made me the keeper of their Vineyards:</hi> ſhe reckons <hi>her preferment</hi> as the proper effect of <hi>their Anger,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that they had wronged her with a miſtaken courteſie, as if ſhe could not have been <hi>ſpited</hi> more than in being prefer'd to a <hi>dignity in Church or State.</hi> And <hi>Jacob</hi> was of the ſame mind too, for though he lov'd <hi>Joſeph</hi> above all his Sons, yet he beſtow'd <hi>the Kingdom</hi> on <hi>Judah,</hi> leſt the enjoyment of <hi>his bleſſing</hi> in this World ſhould have tempted him to <hi>inſolency,</hi> and ſo to the Forfeiture of <hi>Gods bleſſing</hi> in the next.</p>
               <p>Alas the World never embraces any but 'tis like a <hi>Serpent</hi> in <hi>cruelty,</hi> and therefore <hi>Jobs friends</hi> came to him not to <hi>congratulate,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Job 42.10,11.</note> but to <hi>condole</hi> with him the reſtitution of his Fortunes, <hi>quaſi foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix conſolandus ſit de infortunio foelicitatis.</hi> Such a deſperate thing is it for Men to be bewitch't with this <hi>Circean World</hi> that they are never in <hi>greater danger</hi> than when <hi>hedg'd</hi> about with the bleſſings of it; and the <hi>Birth</hi> of Mens Eſtates does ſo often prove the <hi>death</hi> of their Souls, that the <hi>Heathen</hi> reckoned that Man the moſt <hi>unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> in the World who is <hi>alwaies happy,</hi> or rather <hi>never</hi> ſo, becauſe alwayes proſperous. <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                  <hi>Nihil eſt infoelicius eo cui nihil accidit adverſi,</hi> and he <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol'd</hi> his Friend for that very reaſon for which others <hi>applauded</hi> him. <hi>Te judico miſerum, quia non fuiſti miſer;</hi> nor is it only in <hi>his,</hi> but in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103829:17"/> judgment,</hi> that <hi>Rich Men</hi> have very great reaſon to be jealous, leſt the <hi>good things</hi> which they enjoy in this World, like <hi>miſ-imploy'd Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents,</hi> purchaſe for them <hi>evil ones</hi> eternally in the next.</p>
               <p>Since therefore they are ſuch <hi>hindrances</hi> of your eternal happineſs (which I hope you are come hither to mend) methinks I might eaſily perſwade you not to be ſo <hi>over-fond</hi> of them as to make <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ita lucrum temporale ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas ut non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittas aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>forfeiture</hi> of Heaven in the peſuit of them.</p>
               <p>When the Divel <hi>greaſes</hi> you in the <hi>fiſt,</hi> and proffers to <hi>bribe</hi> you out of a good conſcience, return it with St. <hi>Peters zeal, Thy Gold and thy Silver periſh with thee;</hi> and let not this be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or <hi>maxime of trade,</hi> That your ſtock of mony <hi>muſt</hi> be increaſt by <hi>any</hi> means, <hi>Facius rem, recte ſi poſſis, ſi non, quocunquo modo rem,</hi> (I am afraid ſome of you underſtand it better, than an eaſier piece of latine.) They whoſe <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> without the help of the <hi>Philoſophers Stone</hi> can turn any thing <hi>into Gold and Silver</hi> may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily <hi>have</hi> them in abundance; if any Man can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelf to <hi>cheat, defraud, diſſemble, lye demurely, foreſwear ſtrongly, bribe ſome, oppreſs</hi> others, <hi>wrong</hi> all, <hi>ſerve the times</hi> that they may do as much for him, <hi>make uſe of all Men</hi> for his turn, and <hi>ſwallow the greateſt wickedneſs</hi> for the <hi>leaſt advantage,</hi> 'tis a great deal of pitty that he ſhould not be <hi>Rich,</hi> and I ſhall not wonder at his heap of Gold if he can be content to treaſure up ſo much <hi>guilt</hi> with it.</p>
               <p>But I hope you do not ſo fondly <hi>overvalue</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:103829:18"/> Riches, and ſo ambitiouſly <hi>aſpire</hi> to them, as to <hi>pawn</hi> your Souls to the Divel to <hi>take them up,</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ne ſit lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum in arca &amp; damnum in conſcientia.</hi>
                  </note> for that is to <hi>out-bid</hi> his market, and <hi>inhaunce</hi> the price of damnation, whereas you may <hi>be ſure</hi> to go to Hell a great deal <hi>cheaper</hi> than ſo. If you did believe what our Saviour tells you, you would be afraid and ſhy of them upon <hi>any terms,</hi> but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially upon <hi>ſuch,</hi> and neither think your ſelves <hi>frown'd</hi> upon when you <hi>wanted</hi> them, nor ſee any cauſe to be <hi>tranſported</hi> when you <hi>had</hi> them.</p>
               <p>I grudge you not what may be <hi>ſufficient,</hi> not only for the <hi>neceſſity of your perſons,</hi> but likewiſe <hi>for the decency of your Eſtates,</hi> the <hi>neglect</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be <hi>ſordid</hi> and deſervedly <hi>taxible;</hi> but I would not have you ſo much in love with the <hi>fleſh pots of</hi> Aegypt, as not to <hi>forſake</hi> them for <hi>your eternal Canaan,</hi> you ſhould uſe the <hi>World</hi> as a Traveller does his <hi>Inn,</hi> not as if you were to <hi>dwel,</hi> but to <hi>bait</hi> in it. If you do not <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Breviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ad divitias per divitiarum contemtum via eſt. Si ad na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam vives, nunquam eris pauper, ſi ad opinionem, nunquam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves.</hi> Epicur.</note> 
                  <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value</hi> Riches, you will never want them, for 'tis <hi>Opinion</hi> and nothing elſe which makes Men miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Learn to be content with <hi>any thing,</hi> and by this very means you will enjoy <hi>all things,</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnia ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum habet qui nihil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcit, eo quidem certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quam qui cuncta poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det.</hi> Sen.</note> and he who <hi>fils the hungry with good things, and ſends the Rich empty away,</hi> will bleſs you with all Spiritual bleſſings in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus; he will give you <hi>thoſe Riches</hi> which ſhall be <hi>truly amiable,</hi> and the object of your <hi>eternal love;</hi> and therefore fall not in love with the <hi>World,</hi> but <hi>him that made it,</hi> in whoſe power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone it is to make you <hi>rich indeed,</hi> and contemn whilſt you are <hi>alive,</hi> what you cannot enjoy when you are <hi>dead:</hi> For no Man is truly wealthy, who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103829:18"/> cannot carry away what he has with him, for what he leaves behind him is not <hi>his,</hi> but <hi>anothers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never was there more need of a <hi>ſurſum corda</hi> than now, when the Churches invitation to <hi>lift up your hearts,</hi> can hardly prevail with you to raiſe them one jot <hi>above the World;</hi> and therefore ſince I have no great aſſurance to prevail with <hi>you</hi> to <hi>forſake Covetouſneſs,</hi> I pray let me preſs you to <hi>make the beſt of it, to covet earneſtly the beſt gifts,</hi> to be <hi>zealous of ſpiritual gifts; Get wiſdom, get underſtanding,</hi> and ſee that ye <hi>abound in grace,</hi> (<hi>cujus unius honeſta eſt avaritia.</hi> Sen.) Strive to <hi>be rich in good works,</hi> and to <hi>get an intereſt in Chriſt, who of God is made unto us Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption,</hi> and then you can want <hi>nothing</hi> but <hi>what to wiſh for.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.7. <hi>De brev. vitae</hi> cap. 3. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
               </p>
               <p>Look a little into your Eſtates, and examine <hi>all the wayes</hi> by which you have <hi>got</hi> or <hi>encreas'd</hi> them, whither they have been <hi>juſt</hi> or no? Conſider ſeriouſly that if he who <hi>gave nothing to Lazarus</hi> was condemn'd to fry in eternal flames, what will become of them <hi>who took any thing from him?</hi> If they who found <hi>Chriſt naked, and would not cloth him,</hi> muſt be damn'd, what will become of them who <hi>found him cloth'd, and ſtript him?</hi> He whom we hear of <hi>in Hell,</hi> is ſaid <hi>to have riches</hi> and yet <hi>his own</hi> too, not the <hi>Churches</hi> or his <hi>Neighbours Patrimony;</hi> he is noted for <hi>faring deliciouſly</hi> but of his <hi>own bread,</hi> not <hi>for drinking Widows tears inſtead of Wine,</hi> or <hi>eating up Gods People as they eat bread;</hi> we do not read of his <hi>thriving by other Mens loſſes,</hi> making advantage of their <hi>falls,</hi> or inriching himſelf by the <hi>myſtery of breaking;</hi> he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103829:19"/> he is not accus'd for <hi>keeping other mens goods,</hi> but <hi>for not diſtributing his</hi> own, and therefore Hell muſt needs be het ſeven times hotter than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, for <hi>oppreſſing, cheating, ſacrilegious</hi> rich men.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>that part</hi> of your <hi>eſtates</hi> which your conſciences <hi>dare</hi> maintain you <hi>came honeſtly by,</hi> receive it <hi>thankfully,</hi> enjoy it <hi>ſoberly</hi> and <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly,</hi> and communicate it <hi>charitably,</hi> that ſo by your preſent diſpoſure of it, you may make it ſubſervient to an end above its native efficacy, and purchaſe for your ſelves a revenue of <hi>credit</hi> in this world, and <hi>glory</hi> in that to come.</p>
               <p>And this I may the more pardonably invite you to, both becauſe I ſpeak in an age when men are <hi>out of charity</hi> with <hi>Charity it ſelf,</hi> &amp; few ſuch <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Saints</hi> as to have their Religion at <hi>their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ends;</hi> and becauſe Charity is <hi>Ars Quaeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſiſſima,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> and riches yield more profit by their <hi>profuſion</hi> than <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> ſo that by parting with thoſe which you cannot keep, you may gain thoſe which you cannot loſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quas dederis ſolas ſemper habebis opes.</l>
                  <bibl>Mart.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>You ſee 'tis a hard thing to uſe riches well, but 'tis ſo much the more commendable and worthy of your ambition, and therefore I do not preſs you to <hi>throw them away,</hi> but to <hi>lay them out</hi> with ſuch prudence, as to <hi>make you friends of that unrighteous Mammon,</hi> and to take <hi>Daniels</hi> counſel to <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note> to <hi>break off your ſins by righteouſneſs, and your iniquity by ſhewing mercy to the poor, that it may be a lengthening of your tranquility, Honour the Lord with your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103829:19"/> ſubſtance and with the firſt fruits of your increaſe; ſo ſhall your barns be fil'd with plenty, and your preſſes burſt out with new wine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3.9,10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Remember what your <hi>charitable Predeceſſors</hi> have done <hi>in this City</hi> before you; but keep not a regiſter in your memories, of what <hi>you</hi> have done in this ſort <hi>your ſelves;</hi> for the <hi>Welſh</hi> have a <hi>Proverb</hi> that <hi>they who have good memories give but few alms;</hi> becauſe they keep alwaies in mind <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>to whom</hi> they have given before.</p>
               <p>Remember you are <hi>as much</hi> bound to be <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable</hi> as <hi>juſt,</hi> and to <hi>feed the poor</hi> as <hi>not to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and murder</hi> him <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui ſuccur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere perituro cum poteſt, cum non ſuccurrit, occidit.</hi>
                  </note> and then you'l be eaſily perſwaded to uſe <hi>your riches</hi> as you do <hi>your water</hi> with which when you are <hi>ſerved yourſelves,</hi> you let it <hi>flow</hi> freely down to the uſe of others.</p>
               <p>Nor have I any particular <hi>deſign</hi> to drive on, or the leaſt intention to <hi>confine</hi> your charity; but in all ſincerity to exhort you to do <hi>what, when, how, where, to whom,</hi> and <hi>as much</hi> as God and your own conſciences ſhall direct you: and if you have <hi>faith</hi> enough to believe, and <hi>patience</hi> to wait for the reward which Chriſt propoſes, it <hi>will go well with you and with your children after</hi> you, let but <hi>charity</hi> guide your <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> will crown <hi>your heads</hi> eternally.</p>
               <p>Nor are <hi>you</hi> my Brethren of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſo ſecure, but that you may receive <hi>as much prejudice</hi> by your <hi>riches</hi> as any other, take heed therefore that your <hi>preferments,</hi> and <hi>revenues</hi> do not make you the <hi>worſe</hi> for them.</p>
               <p>It was <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his wiſh after his refuſed offers of great preferment, to make <hi>all even</hi> at his <hi>death,</hi> to be out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans debt, and only to have <hi>enough</hi> left to bring him honeſtly to his grave. Let not that which hath hitherto
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103829:20"/> been reputed the <hi>Vice of the City,</hi> be now <hi>juſtly</hi> chargeable on us of <hi>the Clergy;</hi> We of all men are <hi>moſt</hi> ſtrictly ingaged to a perfect <hi>hoſtility</hi> againſt the vanities of the world, and if we are not notoriouſly treacherous to our <hi>own aims</hi> and <hi>intereſts,</hi> our <hi>actions</hi> will declare our ſenſe of it.</p>
               <p>I have no deſire to <hi>judge you,</hi> who are ſo much my bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but if it were poſſible to direct you to <hi>prejudge &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your ſelves,</hi> and ſo either to <hi>anticipate</hi> or <hi>prevent</hi> any further cenſures. I hope <hi>that</hi> for which <hi>ſome perſons</hi> do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn you, is too <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>inferiour gain</hi> for <hi>you</hi> to <hi>ſtoop</hi> to. We have <hi>friends</hi> enough in the World to ſecure us from <hi>that curſe</hi> of our Saviours, <note place="margin">Luke 6.26.</note> 
                  <hi>We be unto you when all Men ſpeak well of you,</hi> and I would it were only <hi>our innocence</hi> which was revil'd. The <hi>mouth of Hell</hi> is now wider open, and the Kingdom in <hi>greater animoſity</hi> againſt <hi>us</hi> than ever, and therefore let not us by our <hi>luxury</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs,</hi> by our <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>griping,</hi> on any ſuch <hi>ſordid</hi> means, as <hi>rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> up our Tenants to the very <hi>ſummum jus</hi> give the <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous People</hi> cauſe to believe that the <hi>defamations</hi> and <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> which the <hi>railing Sectaries</hi> have caſt out againſt us, are <hi>true.</hi> After a long <hi>famine,</hi> you are (bleſſed be God) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd to a <hi>plentifull table;</hi> but take heed of a <hi>ſurfeit,</hi> and that your <hi>plenty</hi> does not make you forget <hi>him</hi> whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you repreſent. Let us remember our <hi>late afflictions and vows</hi> which we made in caſe of a <hi>reſtitution,</hi> and let the <hi>hungry bellies</hi> of the poor and needy who have ſuffer'd with, or like us, experience the <hi>benefit</hi> of our preferments, that the <hi>envious</hi> eye of the worſt of the Laity may not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,</hi> nor the <hi>foul mouths</hi> of the ſcum of the people <hi>rail</hi> at our <hi>large incomes.</hi> And finally,</p>
               <p>Let us all ſuffer our hearts to preach over to our ſelves in private, <hi>the dangers</hi> which have been hinted of <hi>Worldly Riches,</hi> and the <hi>greater hazard</hi> of Salvation that <hi>they</hi> than other men, are in, who enjoy them, and then we ſhall affectionately joyn with the Church in her <hi>collect</hi> for the laſt feſtival, <hi>and pray unto Almighty God that he would grant us grace to forſake all covetous deſires and inordinate love of Riches, and to follow his ſaid Son Jeſus Chriſt, who liveth and reigneth with him and the Holy Ghoſt now and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103829:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
